[SPEAKER_01]: So, you said the dhamma is directly visible.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can see it here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: How is the dhamma directly visible?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the dhamma is founded upon a recognition of the fundamental characteristics of your presently enduring experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the dhamma is not a mystical secret.
[SPEAKER_00]: The dhamma is discernment of what's already there in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's already there in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: My perception, my feelings, my intentions, that's already in front of me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, discerning the nature of those, means seeing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, dhamma is always in the present, and dhamma is always directly visible.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that the dhamma will come through, like, oh, I have to be discerning this, discerning this, and then I'll discern the dhamma on some later occasion, on account of discerning this now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might develop discernment on a later occasion, on account of your efforts, beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: But efforts beforehand, you can't say that that's seeing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you see the dhamma, you saw the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, unless you see the dhamma, you should not regard yourself as somebody who is seeing the dhamma and practicing the dhamma, while at the same time knowing, I haven't seen the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can you unsee?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, of course not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, it's not you doing the seeing or unseeing, it's you discerning on account of what's there anyway.
[SPEAKER_00]: What... on account of things that are there, that cannot not be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you can discern this, or you can want this, or you can choose this, but one thing you cannot do, is not perceive, and not have feelings, and not have intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might want to deny there is a feeling, there is a perception, there is an intention, but your
[SPEAKER_00]: Acceptance, denial, both acceptance and denial, neither acceptance nor denial, mystification of it, is all in response to feeling, perception, intention, that are there on their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what you recognize, if you start discerning the dhamma correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are also indications, those things are indications of body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of course, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That there is a body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there are many different approaches, but they would all be revealing the same principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Presently enduring, presently arisen, presently enduring things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, you are secondary to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your sense of ownership, your sense of choice, it's all real, but as secondary.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, if you start seeing your ownership as secondary, it ceases to be ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, you own this, but I own it more than you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, you're not truly the sole ultimate owner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you own it more than everybody else, but fundamentally, you don't own it, because I own it all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize,
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so I'm only a relative owner.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as such, can you act out of that ultimate view that you are the owner?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha compared generally, like sensuality, or even taking up this body, as like borrowing gold, and borrowing jewelry, and that you enjoy, and then you forget that it's not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're indebted to tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start acting as if it's yours, and then bailiffs come and knock your door through, and just start taking it, everything, and then you feel distressed and suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's your own fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you forgot that it was only borrowed.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... and that's... that's that borrowing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, perception is there whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling is there whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intentions are there whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignoring that they are there on their own, means you automatically took them as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, if you don't take them as yours anymore,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the result of practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those things are still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were never a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was you taking them as yours, while they were not being yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence the discrepancy of suffering and dukkha.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this, is this where conceiving, there's no more conceiving?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, conceiving is on the level of perception paired with the wrong view, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perception of Puthujjana already conceives.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when a Puthujjana perceives his perception, when he feels his feelings, when he intends his intentions,
[SPEAKER_00]: Automatically, just by doing it, so to speak, he does it as it's his own.
[SPEAKER_00]: His view puts himself first, despite the the evidence showing the contrary, which is... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the view, you have the attitude, because these things are there on their own, enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all a puṭṭhujana would need to do is stop fueling that attitude of taking it for granted as I am the first,
[SPEAKER_00]: And start undoing in his own experience, like, what am I feeling right now?
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm feeling, I don't know, quite pleasantly, sort of, elated mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, that's very good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Describe the characteristics and the signs of that mood to yourself, out loud, if you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the first and obvious thing, whenever we've done this in practice with other people, the answer would be, it's just there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so, what would be the signs and characteristics of something that's just there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Means it's kind of independent of you, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just there.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can move it left, I can move it right, I can do this, I can do that, but fundamentally, I could do any of those things because this thing is just there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if something is just there, you haven't created it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was just there, you found it as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, by not thinking these things, puthujjana, just there, means for me, means my, because I already am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that I already am, and for me, and mine, is because this thing is just there, and it's still just there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, when it ceases to be just there, you won't be able to stand a second longer, independently of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's really just about dwelling on these characteristics and knowing how to question yourself rightly, to start discerning the characteristics of things that are in the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha described anicca and dukkha as inherent in all these determinations of your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't say that's impermanent, that's impermanent, that's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said things that determine you are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that determine you are suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, things that you are, are not yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that you are,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not you, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole point here.
[SPEAKER_00]: You recognize things that determine you are these things that are just there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by dwelling on the themes of characteristics of things that are just there, you're actually dwelling on the theme and the characteristics of impermanence, of suffering, as in unsatisfactory, disease.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's just there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it threatening?
[SPEAKER_00]: Who brought this?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody knows how this came to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, it's just there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, my whole experience is directed upon, determined by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: What if this goes?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That thing stands upon that which I've got no access to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the thought that it stands upon that, already stands upon that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the basis of feeling that thing that's already there... Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's inconceivable to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like you're looking for a great revelation, epiphany.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just dwelling on those particular characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that, in itself, is going to result in basically diminishing of the symptoms of non-dwelling on those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not dwelling on things just being there, by not dwelling on that impermanence, you automatically assume permanence, you automatically assume ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: By dwelling on that, oh, this is just there, independent of me, kind of indifferent to me, I can react, I can do this, but fundamentally, I can do any of it, because this thing is enduring on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Discerning that more and more, means discerning the theme of impermanence more and more, which then automatically means discerning the theme of this is more and more, dukkha, and results in the experience of not being taken as myself.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if one has... starts having views about, say, feelings, why they're there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Feelings are there because... See, you can even... you can even... the only reason you're even able to ask such question, why are feelings there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because feeling is there during on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean any thought, any response, any logical, rational turn is already secondary to this thing being there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why dhamma is beyond thinking, as in attāka, which cannot be reasoned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean it's mystical.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means that movements of your reason cannot stand for that because of which these movements are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cannot stand for the nature of things, which is what dhamma is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as we've shown, you can still use these movements to learn how to look the opposite direction of the movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: To look at the source of the movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Source being yoniso, like yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have a... oh, how are these feelings there?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is my feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's a movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a rational thought question.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, instead of just trying to find another rational answer, you start looking for the direction where this question is pointing at.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, the fact that you can ask, well, what is my current feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, the feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your designation, your directing of the question,
[SPEAKER_00]: Would not be possible if the feeling is not there enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might not know the particulars of the feeling, but the fact that, even in the most ambiguous terms, you go, how do I feel now?
[SPEAKER_00]: There is some sense of the direction where the feeling is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But instead of providing the answer, you start looking down that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: How am I feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I'm not sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so that lack of... lack of kind of... being not sure, how does that feel then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it kind of feels a bit pressing.
[SPEAKER_00]: What does pressure feel like?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, so then, me not being sure how I feel slightly pressured by it, means I feel unpleasantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fundamentally, on a subtle level, it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: What are the characteristics of that unpleasant feeling that's presently enduring while I'm asking these questions?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, see, like, as I said, you use the movements of your question, but you don't follow the direction of the movement.
[SPEAKER_00]: You look at the source of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You learn how to see
[SPEAKER_00]: The background of that movement, the foundation, the source, which is literally, boom, of the... where the movement came from.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha meant by yoni... yoniso, yoni means boom, literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you learn how to attend the source, as opposed to attend what that sort of question points you at.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you get to discern more and more characteristics of that which is already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That feeling is already there, whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mood is already there, whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I talk about the mood because the mood is kind of a blend between general perception and general feeling, how you feel it, which is basically the mood is where your mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't see directly, oh, this is my mood.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always behind you.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you never learn how to look in the direction from that source, you can never see it, which means you're always going to be affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's when people go through their moods, like on a daily basis, up and down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And someone who doesn't see their mind, or the signs of the mind... Means they're automatically affected by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so in solitude...
[SPEAKER_00]: In solitude, it's going to become hard to not see the signs of your mind, which is why people who exist in the mode of avoiding the states of the... avoiding seeing the states of the mind, but just going with what direction is offered through their senses,
[SPEAKER_00]: Distraction, sensuality, ill-will, I'm angry, I'm sad, I'm happy, I'm lustful, I'm this, I'm this, I'm this... Never stop and look at the source of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why those people are terrified of solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: It feels like drowning, literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more of existence you go used to, the threshold of being of that bhāva, it's not being matched.
[SPEAKER_00]: There isn't that level of engagement, that level of... of sort of a degree of consciousness in those things, and you feel like you're drowning.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why people get panic attacks and anxieties and...
[SPEAKER_00]: Dread and overwhelm, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just by solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go mad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't go mad because of the solitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go mad on account of not being able to fulfill the habits of avoiding solitude that you existentially depend upon.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you go mad.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you start undoing those habits, you start seeing solitude as pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start seeing boredom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, boredom has negative connotation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Neutral, neither pleasant or unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start feeling as lofty and pleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, boredom is a neutral feeling from the point of view of unmatched, unmet habits of distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm bored, because I still assume I must be doing something.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to be doing something.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's nothing I have to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't do now, or nothing that I particularly want to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm kind of a bit bored.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stay with that boredom, and then that discrepancy is going to get amplified.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, your dependence on needing to do something, including practice meditation, and doing this, and watch my breath,
[SPEAKER_00]: And not meeting it, like on the existential level or presently doing things, and that that's when that boredom becomes anxiety and fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as I said, it's determined by your dependence on doing things, not by the actual solitude and neutral feeling.